Guide to the Jay C. Waldman Papers, 1968-2003 AIS.2007.10
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Jay C. Waldman Papers
1968-2003
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Waldman, Jay C.
AIS.2007.10
30 Linear Feet (24 boxes)
The Jay C. Waldman Papers document the fifteen years (1971-1986) Waldman served as a close aide to Dick Thornburgh. Waldman first joined Thornburgh in 1971 when Thornburgh was serving as United States Attorney for Western Pennsylvania, later went with him to Washington, D.C. to the Criminal Division at the United States Department of Justice, and subsequently returned to Pennsylvania with Thornburgh in 1977 to manage his successful Campaign for Governor. He then served as the Executive Assistant to the Governor and General Counsel until 1986 when he returned to the private practice of law in Philadelphia. The collection includes material such as correspondence, memoranda, issue research and polling, news clips, and legal case documents.
Biography
The Jay C. Waldman Papers document the fifteen years that he served as a close aide to Dick Thornburgh in his political career in the U.S. Department of Justice and as Pennsylvania Governor. As advisor to Thornburgh, Waldman also played a pivotal role in Pennsylvania government. Thornburgh's dedication to Waldman in his autobiography, Where the Evidence Leads, describes the relationship best: "To my friend, colleague and mentor."
Waldman graduated from University of Wisconsin in 1966, where he received honors in History and Political Science, and from the University of Pennsylvania Law School in 1969. Following law school, he served as law clerk to Pittsburgh Judge Gwilym A. Price, Jr. and briefly was an associate at Rose, Schmidt & Dixon in Pittsburgh.
Waldman became known early on for his keen intellect and insights and accordingly served in major roles throughout Thornburgh's years of public service. In May 1971, Waldman first joined Thornburgh, then U.S. Attorney for Western Pennsylvania. When Thornburgh moved on to serve as Assistant Attorney General, Criminal Division, U.S. Department of Justice, Washington, D.C., Waldman accompanied him and served as Deputy Assistant Attorney General responsible for the Division's Organized Crime and Racketeering Section, Narcotic and Dangerous Drug Section, and Public Integrity Section, as well as the management of litigation for these operations from July 1975 to 1977.
Thornburgh returned to Pittsburgh to run for Governor in 1977; Waldman soon joined him and served as his Campaign Manager. Waldman's winning 1978 campaign strategies proved to be exceptional, particularly as Waldman had never run a campaign before. He subsequently served as executive assistant and legal counsel during Thornburgh's years as Governor of Pennsylvania from 1979 to 1986. The Spring 2004 issue of the "Penn Journal" said, "Those who had the good fortune to know and work with Judge Waldman during these years, witnessed the workings of a brilliant political mind." After leaving the Thornburgh Administration, Waldman practiced law in Philadelphia and was nominated to the U.S. District Court for the Eastern District of Pennsylvania in 1988, serving on the federal bench for 14 years. At the time of his death in 2003, it was expected that he would be elevated to the 3rd U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals.
Scope and Content Notes
The material in this collection reflects the expansive responsibilities Waldman amassed in his fifteen years of service as an aide to Dick Thornburgh. In addition to his native ability and advice, it is well known and documented that Waldman and Thornburgh not only worked well together, but also respected and admired one another. Waldman's collection and that of Dick Thornburgh's are significantly linked together, as many topics and issues are specifically intertwined. The collection contains correspondence, memoranda, issues, research and polling, news clippings, and legal case documents. The majority of the materials in this collection date from 1968 to 2003.
Waldman's contributions in each of his fifteen years of public service are reflected in these personal papers. However, as one who did not commit much to paper, the files are diverse and thin in some respects. They do reflect Waldman's expansive responsibilities in each position and the issues addressed. Waldman's ideas are particularly well represented in his memoranda during the first campaign for governor (1977-1978) and in reports and memoranda to Dick Thornburgh in Department of Justice years.
Waldman's official files from his gubernatorial years (1979-1986) are held by the Pennsylvania Historical and Museum Commission as part of the Dick Thornburgh Governor files: collection MC-404. Waldman's, as Executive Assistant and General Counsel, are within that collection: 4-2825.
Arrangement
Series I. Office of the United States Attorney, Western Pennsylvania, 1965-1975
Series II. Criminal Division, United States Department of Justice, 1975-1977
Series III. Campaign for Governor Consultants, 1977-1978
Series IV. Campaign for Governor Opposition Research, 1977-1978
Series V. Campaign for Governor Issues, 1977-1978
Series VI. Campaign for Governor Primary Election, 1977-1978
Series VII. Campaign for Governor General Election, 1978
Series VIII. Gubernatorial Transition, 1978
Series IX. Re-election Campaign for Governor, 1979-1983
Series X. Office of the Governor, 1979-1986
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Roberta Waldman in 2007.
Custodial History
The Waldman files came from his office and home following his untimely death in 2003. They were collected, boxed and ultimately kindly donated to the University of Pittsburgh by his wife, Roberta Waldman. Some files and papers were loose in boxes, some foldered, many not. Where Waldman had assorted folders in large accordion files or others titled specifically by him, that order has been maintained.
Previous Citation
Jay C. Waldman Papers, 1968-2003, AIS.2007.10, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
Dick Thornburgh Papers, AIS.1998.30, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Peter F. Flaherty Papers, 1964-1995, AIS.1999.19. Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Pennsylvania Historical and Museum Commission: Waldman
Separated Material
All media material including tapes and recordings are housed separately in media storage.
Pennsylvania -- Politics and government -- 20th century; United States -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Correspondence; Memorandums; Lawyers -- Pennsylvania; Legal documents; Clippings (Information artifacts); Lawyers -- United States; Organized crime -- United States; Politics; Campaign management -- Pennsylvania; Personal papers; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Harrisburg (Pa.); Philadelphia (Pa.); Washington (D.C.); Political campaigns -- Pennsylvania; Pennsylvania. Governor -- Elections, 1978; United States. Department of Justice. Public Integrity Section; Pennsylvania. Office of the Governor. Office of General Counsel; Pennsylvania. Office of the Governor; Thornburgh, Dick; United States. Attorney (Pennsylvania: Western District); United States. Attorney-General; United States. Department of Justice. Criminal Division. Narcotic and Dangerous Drug Section; United States. Department of Justice. Criminal Division. Organized Crime and Racketeering Section; Waldman, Jay C.
- Office of the United States Attorney, Western Pennsylvania, 1965-1975; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  In June 1970, the office of Dick Thornburgh, who was then serving as United States Attorney for Western Pennsylvania, was allocated funds for four additional Assistant United States Attorneys. One of those subsequently hired was Jay C. Waldman. Unbeknownst at that time to either Thornburgh or Waldman, the latter was to serve a major role in Thornburgh's ongoing public career. Waldman continued in the U.S. Attorney's office until 1975 when he moved to Washington D.C., joining Thornburgh who had been named Deputy Assistant Attorney General in charge of the Criminal Division of the Department of Justice. The files are presented in the following five subseries: Pre-Appointment, Waldman Assistant U.S. Attorney Files, United States Attorney's Office Files, Waldman Case Files, and Reference Notes. The materials in this series date from 1965 to 1975.
  - Pre-Appointment, 1965-1971; 1.
    These files precede Waldman's years in the United States Attorney's office. The materials in this subseries consist of records from Waldman's law school years at University of Pennsylvania, a folder of decisions by Judge Gwilym A. Price, for whom Waldman clerked, and some other case notes and references from brief employment at Rose, Schmidt and Dixon, a Pittsburgh law firm. The materials date from 1965 to 1971.
    - Law School, Taxation, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Law School, Labor Law, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Law School, Labor Law, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Law School, Cases and class bios, 1966, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Judge Price Decisions, January-June 1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Pittsburgh Court of Common Pleas Civil Division Cases, 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Memos, Rose Schmidt & Dixon, Aircraft, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Memos, Rose Schmidt & Dixon, Westinghouse, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Waldman Assistant U.S. Attorney Files, 1970-1975; 2.
    This subseries documents Waldman's years as Assistant U.S. Attorney. His specific case files are contained in Subseries 4. Waldman Case Files. The subjects of the material include an early biography, a commendation, bar admissions research, correspondence to and from, memos to and from, memos to Blair A. Griffith enumerating case updates in 1975, ephemera, and Pittsburgh Mayoral Campaign 1972. The materials in this subseries date from 1970 to June 1975.
    - JCW Bio and personal, 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Research re admission to bar, August 1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Memos to JCW, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Memos from JCW, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Memos to Blair Griffith, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - AG Levi Outstanding Performance Award, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Pittsburgh Mayoral election, polling and memos re Thornburgh for Mayor, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Committee for election of Thornburgh for Mayor, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Tabor for Mayor, brochures, ephemera, endorsement, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Tabor Neighborhood Research Program, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Tabor for Mayor, mailings, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Tabor lists, donors, mailings, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - U.S. Attorney Office Files, 1970-1975; 3.
    This subseries contains general files pertaining to the office of the U.S. Attorney, such as news releases, news clips, accomplishments of the office, miscellaneous correspondence, and cases by other office attorneys. The files date from 1970 to June 1975.
    - News Releases, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - News clips and accomplishments, 1969-1975 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - USA office cases, not JCW, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Waldman Case Files, 1970-1975; 4.
    This subseries pertains specifically to cases Waldman identified and are grouped as Civil, Criminal, Appeals, Orphans Court, or Obscenity. Printed Court Cases are grouped together by year. In some files there are briefs, many include Waldman's handwritten notes as well as other relevant case and legal information. Where notes and legal materials were not obviously associated with a specific case, see Subseries 5. Miscellaneous Notes. The obscenity material is extensive and relates to several cases. The material is broken up into multiple files but collectively in Waldman's original order. The materials date from 1970 to June 1975.
    - Cases, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Cases, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Cases, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Cases, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Cases, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Case Civil, Ponderendolph, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Case Civil, Quinones, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Case Civil, Mickelic, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Case Civil, Briefs, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Case Criminal, Hobbs material, and Mazzei, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Case Criminal, Olen, laws re, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Case Criminal, Olen, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Case Criminal, Olen, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Case Criminal, Faix documents, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Case Criminal, Faix with appeal, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Case Criminal, Fiore, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Cases Criminal, Notes and Documents, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Cases Criminal, Notes and Documents, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Cases Criminal, Notes and Documents, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Cases Appeal, Harris, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Cases Appeal, Harris, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Cases Appeal, miscellaneous, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Case Orphans Court, Lizenkon, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Cases, Miscellaneous Notes, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Obscenity, Cases, Notes, and References, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Obscenity, Cases, Notes, and References, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Obscenity, Cases, Notes, and References, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Obscenity, Cases, other states, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Reference Notes, 1970-1975; 5.
    The material in this subseries mainly consists of miscellaneous notes and documents. Waldman's handwritten notes and reference files relate to multiple subjects, but were not labeled or kept with a particular case. However, these files do relate to several of the cases in Series 1. Office United States Attorney, Western Pennsylvania. The material in this subseries dates from 1970 to 1975.
    - JCW handwritten notes on cases, 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Reference documents, 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Reference documents, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Criminal Division, United States Department of Justice, 1975-1977; II.
  Waldman moved with Thornburgh to Washington in 1975 when Thornburgh was named Assistant Attorney General in charge of the Criminal Division. Waldman began as Special Assistant to Thornburgh and was promoted to Deputy Assistant Attorney General with responsibility for overseeing organized crime, official corruption, and narcotics matters within the department and the U.S. Attorneys' offices. Waldman briefly continued in this position after March 1977 when Thornburgh returned to Pennsylvania. He then resigned on July 15th after working for those few months under Pete Flaherty, who was Thornburgh successor at the Department of Justice as Deputy Attorney General. The material in this series includes memos, correspondence, organization charts, case research, speeches, and departmental issues. This series is further subdivided into five subseries: Waldman/Thornburgh Files, Departmental Reorganization, Strike Forces, Cases/Issues, and Department Files. The dates here are from 1974 to 1977. Additional relevant research files can be found in the Dick Thornburgh Papers housed at the Archives Service Center.
  - Waldman/Thornburgh Files, 1975-1977; 1.
    The memoranda contained in this subseries served as the principal method of communication within the division regarding department personnel, cases, and legal investigations. Both correspondence and memos to and from Waldman (JCW), Thornburgh (RLT), and others contain much substantive information about cases as well as other departmental matters of note. There is also correspondence from Waldman and Thornburgh containing miscellaneous speeches and articles by and about Thornburgh. Additionally, Thornburgh's appointment as Deputy Attorney General and his resignation from the department are included in this subseries. The materials in this subseries date from 1975 to 1977.
    - JCW Appointments and bios, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - JCW Memos from, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - JCW Correspondence from, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - JCW Correspondence to, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - JCW Reading File, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - JCW Speeches/Testimony, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - RLT Schweiker comment re DT appointment, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - RLT Memos to, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - RLT Memos from, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - RLT Correspondence from, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - RLT Speeches, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - RLT Articles by, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - RLT Appointed Deputy Attorney General, February 8, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - RLT Resignation correspondence to AG Bell, and President Carter, March 1977 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Departmental Reorganization, 1975-1977; 2.
    This subseries pertains to the time when Thornburgh assigned Waldman and Seif, his two principal aides, to conduct a top-to-bottom review of the division's management structure at the very outset of their arrival in Washington in 1975. This ultimately resulted in wide-spread and often especially difficult personnel changes, including the replacement or reassignment of most deputies and section chiefs. Additionally, a Public Integrity Section was created, which was a major contribution to accomplishments of the tenure of Thornburgh and Waldman. Related research, correspondence, drafts and comprehensive reports in this subseries enumerate the complexities associated with this reorganization and include the final report to Attorney General Griffin Bell. The material in this subseries dates from 1975 to 1977.
    - JCW handwritten notes, personnel and organization, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - JCW handwritten organization chart, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Memoranda, May, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Scarlata memoranda and notes, May 1975 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Scarlata memoranda with RLT annotations, May 1975 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Memoranda and draft briefings, July-October 1975 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Review of Criminal Division, November 1975 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Memorandum, December 5, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Memorandum, December 16, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Memoranda, February 1976 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Draft Criminal Division report and recommendations to Attny General, September 1976 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Draft report and recommendations, September 1976 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Final Report and Recommendations to Attny Gen, September 10, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Draft memorandum to Attny General Bell, January 17, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Memorandum to Attny General Bell, The Criminal Division, January 28, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Strike Forces, 1976-1977; 3.
    Material in this subseries directly relates to the organized crime "Strike Forces." Waldman had experience with the Strike Forces and related controversies from his years with Thornburgh in the U.S. Attorney's office in Pittsburgh. There was pressure in the Criminal Division to integrate them into the Organized Crime and Racketeering Section, with Waldman in charge of organized crime and related issues. The future of the "Strike Forces" was only decided in the fall of 1976. What ensued was an office-by-office appraisal of the various strike forces which is well documented in this material. Some strike forces were disbanded, others "folded in" to U.S. Attorneys' offices, and some kept in operation but under much stricter guidelines which are enumerated in a December 1976 report. The materials date from 1976 to 1977.
    - Guidelines, August-September 1976 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Guidelines, October-November 1976 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Guidelines, December 1976 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Organized Crime Program, December 1976 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence and reports, January-March 1977 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Evaluations, May-August 1976 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Evaluations, New York, Connolly Issue, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Evaluations, New York, Connolly Issue, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Evaluations, Pittsburgh, Brooklyn, Los Angeles, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Evaluations, Newark, Detroit, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Evaluations, New Orleans, St. Louis, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Cases/Issues, 1975-1977; 4.
    These files specifically relate to cases handled by the Criminal Division. Although it is not certain whether or not Waldman was specifically in charge of these, he was involved with the research and outcomes. Several files are on issues involving personnel matters intertwined with cases that were vexing and serious; "Curren" is one example of a case that goes into considerable detail. The materials in this subseries date from 1975 to 1977.
    - Tax Reform Act of 1976 (HB 10612) Revision, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 06-12)
    - IRS/DOJ guidelines and jurisdiction, 1975-1977 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - S495, Watergate Reorganization and Reform of 1976 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - S495, DT folder with annotations, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Watergate, President Form and Dean Allegations, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - US Attorney Curren issue, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - US Attorney Curren issue, January-February, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - US Attorney Curren issue, March-May, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - US Attorney Curren issue, November 1976-April 1977 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - HR 214, Right to Privacy Act, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Case, Olen/Ezrine, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Case, Olen/Ezrine, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Case, Cutler/Cesario, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Departmental Files, 1970-1977; 5.
    The files in this subseries generally pertain to the department and are generated by others rather than Waldman or Thornburgh. There are news releases, press clippings, memoranda, files of testimonies of Attorneys General Levi and Bell, and some files from March 1977 to July 1977, when Peter Flaherty (PF) had been appointed to the Department of Justice. Waldman resigned from the department in July 1977, and returned to Pennsylvania. These materials date from 1975 to 1977.
    - Clippings, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - News releases, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Resumes, memos, correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - "DC Legislation", 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Testimony AGs Levi and Bell, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - JCW PA politics, 1970-1977 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - JCW Resignation, July 1977 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - JCW Legislation memos, March 1977 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - PF Memos and testimony, March-July 1977 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - PF Miscellaneous, June 1977 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - PF Correspondence, speech, resignation, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Campaign for Governor Consultants, 1969-1978; III.
  This series contains plans that were submitted by consultants seeking to represent and guide the Dick Thornburgh campaign for governor. Many were submitted spontaneously and in fact more than one consultant was used. Lance Tarrence provided much information, and David Garth was contracted for the primary election. Roger Ailes and Bailey/Deardourff were used in the general election. The plans are very detailed, many highly statistical, and frequently included polls/questionnaires to determine and convey potential outcomes. These were relevant not only regarding voters' attitudes about candidates, but also for identifying issues of concern to the voters.